[
  {
    "question": "If 2q3<sub>5</sub> = 77<sub>8</sub>, find q",
    "option_a": "2",
    "option_b": "1",
    "option_c": "4",
    "option_d": "O",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "2q3<sub>5</sub> = 77<sub>8</sub> <br> 2 x 52 + q x 51 + 3 x 50 = 7 x 81 + 7 x 80 <br> 2 x 25 + q x 5 + 3 x 1 = 7 x 8 + 7 x 1 <br> 50 + 5q + 3 = 56 + 7 <br> 5q = 63 - 53 <br> q = \\(\\frac{10}{5}\\) <br> q = 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Simplify \\(\\frac{3\\frac{2}{3} \\times \\frac{5}{6} \\times \\frac{2}{3}}{\\frac{11}{15} \\times \\frac{3}{4} \\times \\frac{2}{27}}\\)",
    "option_a": "\\(5\\frac{2}{3}\\)",
    "option_b": "30",
    "option_c": "\\(4\\frac{1}{3}\\)",
    "option_d": "50",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "\\(\\frac{3\\frac{2}{3} \\times \\frac{5}{6} \\times \\frac{2}{3}}{\\frac{11}{15} \\times \\frac{3}{4} \\times \\frac{2}{27}}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{\\frac{11}{3} \\times \\frac{5}{6} \\times \\frac{2}{3}}{\\frac{11}{15} \\times \\frac{3}{4} \\times \\frac{2}{27}}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{110}{54} \\div \\frac{66}{1620}\\) <br> 50"
  },
  {
    "question": "A man invested N5,000 for 9 months at 4%. What is the simple interest?",
    "option_a": "N150",
    "option_b": "N220",
    "option_c": "N130",
    "option_d": "N250",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "S.I. = \\(\\frac{P \\times R \\times T}{100}\\) <br> If T = 9 months, it is equivalent to \\(\\frac{9}{12}\\) years <br> S.I. = \\(\\frac{5000 \\times 4 \\times 9}{100 \\times 12}\\) <br> S.I. = N150"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the numbers M, N, Q are in the ratio 5:4:3, find the value of \\(\\frac{2N - Q}{M}\\)",
    "option_a": "2",
    "option_b": "3",
    "option_c": "1",
    "option_d": "4",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "M:N:Q == 5:4:3 <br> i.e M = 5, N = 4, q = 3 <br> Substituting values into equation, we have... <br> \\(\\frac{2N - Q}{M}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac{2(4) - 3}{5}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac{8 - 3}{5}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac{5}{5}\\) <br> = 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Simplify \\((\\frac{16}{81})^{\\frac{1}{4}} \\div (\\frac{9}{16})^{-\\frac{1}{2}}\\)",
    "option_a": "\\(\\frac{2}{3}\\)",
    "option_b": "\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
    "option_c": "\\(\\frac{8}{9}\\)",
    "option_d": "\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "\\((\\frac{16}{81})^{\\frac{1}{4}} \\div (\\frac{9}{16})^{-\\frac{1}{2}}\\) <br> \\((\\frac{16}{81})^{\\frac{1}{4}} \\div (\\frac{16}{9})^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\) <br> \\((\\frac{2^4}{3^4})^{\\frac{1}{4}} \\div (\\frac{4^2}{3^2})^{\\frac{1}{2}}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{2^{4 \\times \\frac{1}{4}}}{3^{4 \\times \\frac{1}{4}}} \\div \\frac{4^{2 \\times \\frac{1}{2}}}{3^{2 \\times \\frac{1}{2}}}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{2}{3} \\div \\frac{4}{3}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{2}{3} \\times \\frac{3}{4}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{2}{4}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)"
  },
  {
    "question": "If log<sub>3</sub>18 + log<sub>3</sub>3 - log<sub>3</sub>x = 3, Find x.",
    "option_a": "1",
    "option_b": "2",
    "option_c": "o",
    "option_d": "3",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": " log\\(_{3}^{18}\\) + log\\(_{3}^{3}\\) - log\\(_{3}^{x}\\) = 3 <br> log\\(_{3}^{18}\\) + log\\(_{3}^{3}\\) - log\\(_{3}^{x}\\) =  3log33 <br> log\\(_{3}^{18}\\) + log\\(_{3}^{3}\\) - log\\(_{3}^{x}\\) = log333 <br> log3(\\(\\frac{18 \\times 3}{X}\\)) = log333 <br> \\(\\frac{18 \\times 3}{X}\\) = 33 <br> 18 x 3 = 27 x X <br> x = \\(\\frac{18 \\times 3}{27}\\) <br> = 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Rationalize \\(\\frac{2 - \\sqrt5}{3 - \\sqrt5}\\)",
    "option_a": "\\(\\frac{1 - \\sqrt5}{2}\\)",
    "option_b": "\\(\\frac{1 - \\sqrt5}{4}\\)",
    "option_c": "\\(\\frac{ \\sqrt5 - 1}{2}\\)",
    "option_d": "\\(\\frac{1 + \\sqrt5}{4}\\)",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "\\(\\frac{2 - \\sqrt5}{3 - \\sqrt5}\\) x \\(\\frac{3 + \\sqrt5}{3 + \\sqrt5}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{(2 - \\sqrt5)(3 + \\sqrt5)}{(3 - \\sqrt5)(3 + \\sqrt5)}\\) = \\(\\frac{6 +2\\sqrt5 - 3\\sqrt5 - \\sqrt25}{9 + 3\\sqrt5 - 3\\sqrt5 - \\sqrt25}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac{6 - \\sqrt5 - 5}{9 - 5}\\)  <br> = \\(\\frac{1 - \\sqrt5}{4}\\)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Simplify (\\(\\sqrt2 + \\frac{1}{\\sqrt3})(\\sqrt2 - \\frac{1}{\\sqrt3}\\))",
    "option_a": "\\(\\frac{7}{3}\\)",
    "option_b": "\\(\\frac{5}{3}\\)",
    "option_c": "\\(\\frac{5}{2}\\)",
    "option_d": "\\(\\frac{3}{2}\\)",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "(\\(\\sqrt2 + \\frac{1}{\\sqrt3})(\\sqrt2 - \\frac{1}{\\sqrt3}\\)) <br> \\(\\sqrt4 - \\frac {\\sqrt2}{\\sqrt3} + \\frac {\\sqrt2}{\\sqrt3} - \\frac {1}{\\sqrt9}\\) <br> = 2 - \\(\\frac {1}{3}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac {16 - 1}{3}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac{5}{3}\\)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Raial has 7 different posters to be hanged in her bedroom, living room and kitchen. Assuming she has plans to place at least a poster in each of the 3 rooms, how many choices does she have?",
    "option_a": "49",
    "option_b": "170",
    "option_c": "21",
    "option_d": "210",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "The first poster has 7 ways to be arranges, the second poster can be arranged in 6 ways and the third poster in 5 ways.  <br> = 7 x 6 x 5  <br> = 210 ways  <br> or \\(\\frac{7}{P_3}\\) = \\(\\frac{7!}{(7 - 3)!}\\) = \\(\\frac{7!}{4!}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac{7 \\times 6 \\times 5 \\times 4!}{4!}\\)  <br> = 210 ways"
  },
  {
    "question": "Make R the subject of the formula if T = \\(\\frac {KR^2 + M}{3}\\)",
    "option_a": "\\(\\sqrt\\frac{3T - K}{M}\\)",
    "option_b": "\\(\\sqrt\\frac{3T - M}{K}\\)",
    "option_c": "\\(\\sqrt\\frac{3T + K}{M}\\)",
    "option_d": "\\(\\sqrt\\frac{3T - K}{M}\\)",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "T = \\(\\frac{KR^2 + M}{3}\\) <br> 3T = KR2 + M  <br> KR2 = 3T - M <br> R2 = \\(\\frac{3T - M}{K}\\) <br> R = \\(\\sqrt\\frac{3T - M}{K}\\)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Find the remainder when X<sup>3<sup> - 2X<sup>2</sup> + 3X - 3 is divided by X<sup>2</sup> + 1",
    "option_a": "2X - 1",
    "option_b": "X + 3",
    "option_c": "2X + 1",
    "option_d": "X - 3",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "X<sup>2</sup> + 1 \\(\\frac{X - 2}{\\sqrt{X^3 - 2X^2 + 3n - 3}}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac {- 6X^3 + n}{-2X^2 + 2X - 3}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac{(-2X^2 - 2)}{2X - 1}\\) <br> Remainder is 2X - 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Factorize completely 9y<sup>2</sup> - 16X<sup>2</sup>",
    "option_a": "(3y - 2x)(3y + 4x)",
    "option_b": "(3y + 4x)(3y + 4x)",
    "option_c": "(3y + 2x)(3y - 4x)",
    "option_d": "(3y - 4x)(3y + 4x)",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "9y<sup>2</sup> - 16x<sup>2</sup> <br> = 32y<sup>2</sup> - 42x<sup>2</sup> <br> = (3y - 4x)(3y +4x)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Solve for x and y respectively in the simultaneous equations -2x - 5y = 3. x + 3y = 0",
    "option_a": "-3, -9",
    "option_b": "9, -3",
    "option_c": "-9,3",
    "option_d": "3, -9",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "-2x -5y = 3  <br> x + 3y = 0  <br> x = -3y <br> -2 (-3y) - 5y = -3 <br> 6y - 5y = 3 <br> y = 3 <br> but, x = -3y  <br> x = -3(3) <br> x = -9 <br> therefore, x = -9, y = 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "If x varies directly as square root of y and x = 81 when y = 9, Find x when y = 1\\(\\frac{7}{9}\\)",
    "option_a": "20\\(\\frac{1}{4}\\)",
    "option_b": "27",
    "option_c": "2\\(\\frac{1}{4}\\)",
    "option_d": "36",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "x \\(\\alpha\\sqrt y\\) <br> x = k\\(\\sqrt y\\) <br> 81 = k\\(\\sqrt9\\) <br> k = \\(\\frac{81}{3}\\) <br> = 27 <br> therefore, x = 27\\(\\sqrt y\\)  <br> y = 1\\(\\frac{7}{9}\\) = \\(\\frac{16}{9}\\) <br> x = 27 x \\(\\sqrt{\\frac{16}{9}}\\) <br> = 27 x \\(\\frac{4}{3}\\) <br> dividing 27 by 3  <br> = 9 x 4  <br> = 36"
  },
  {
    "question": "T varies inversely as the cube of R. When R = 3, T = \\(\\frac{2}{81}\\), find T when R = 2",
    "option_a": "\\(\\frac{1}{18}\\)",
    "option_b": "\\(\\frac{1}{12}\\)",
    "option_c": "\\(\\frac{1}{24}\\)",
    "option_d": "\\(\\frac{1}{6}\\)",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "T \\(\\alpha \\frac{1}{R^3}\\) <br> T = \\(\\frac{k}{R^3}\\) <br> k = TR3 <br> = \\(\\frac{2}{81}\\) x 33 <br> = \\(\\frac{2}{81}\\) x 27 <br> dividing 81 by 27  <br> k = \\(\\frac{2}{2}\\) <br> therefore, T = \\(\\frac{2}{3}\\) x \\(\\frac{1}{R^3}\\) <br> When R = 2  <br> T = \\(\\frac{2}{3}\\) x \\(\\frac{1}{2^3}\\) = \\(\\frac{2}{3}\\) x \\(\\frac{1}{8}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac{1}{12}\\)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Solve the inequality -6(x + 3) \\(\\leq\\) 4(x - 2)",
    "option_a": "x \\(\\leq\\) 2",
    "option_b": "x \\(\\geq\\) -1",
    "option_c": "x \\(\\geq\\) -2",
    "option_d": "x \\(\\leq\\) -1",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "-6(x + 3) \\(\\leq\\) 4(x - 2) <br> -6(x +3) \\(\\leq\\) 4(x - 2) <br> -6x -18 \\(\\leq\\) 4x - 8  <br> -18 + 8 \\(\\leq\\) 4x +6x  <br> -10x \\(\\leq\\) 10x  <br> 10x \\(\\leq\\) -10  <br> x \\(\\leq\\) 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Solve the inequality x<sup>2</sup> + 2x > 15.",
    "option_a": "x < -3 or x > 5",
    "option_b": "-5 < x < 3",
    "option_c": "x < 3 or x > 5",
    "option_d": "x > 3 or x < -5",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "x<sup>2</sup> + 2x > 15  <br> x<sup>2</sup> + 2x - 15 > 0  <br> (x<sup>2</sup> + 5x) - (3x - 15) > 0  <br> x(x + 5) - 3(x + 5) >0 <br> (x - 3)(x + 5) > 0  <br> therefore, x = 3 or -5  <br> then x < -5 or x > 3 <br> i.e. x< 3 or x < -5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Find the sum of the first 18 terms of the series 3, 6, 9,..., 36.",
    "option_a": "505",
    "option_b": "513",
    "option_c": "433",
    "option_d": "635",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "3, 6, 9,..., 36. <br> a = 3, d = 3, i = 36, n = 18 <br> Sn = \\(\\frac{n}{2}\\) [2a + (n - 1)d <br> S18 = \\(\\frac{18}{2}\\) [2 x 3 + (18 - 1)3] <br> = 9[6 + (17 x 3)] <br> = 9 [6 + 51] = 9(57) <br> = 513"
  },
  {
    "question": "The seconds term of a geometric series is 4 while the fourth term is 16. Find the sum of the first five terms",
    "option_a": "60",
    "option_b": "62",
    "option_c": "54",
    "option_d": "64",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": ""
  },
  {
    "question": "A binary operation \\(\\oplus\\) om real numbers is defined by x \\(\\oplus\\) y = xy + x + y for two real numbers x and y. Find the value of 3 \\(\\oplus\\) - \\(\\frac{2}{3}\\).",
    "option_a": "- \\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)",
    "option_b": "\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)",
    "option_c": "-1",
    "option_d": "2",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "N + Y = XY + X + Y  <br> 3 + -\\(\\frac{2}{3}\\) = 3(- \\(\\frac{2}{3}\\)) + 3 + (- \\(\\frac{2}{3}\\)) <br> = -2 + 3 -\\(\\frac{2}{3}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac{1 - 2}{1 - 3}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)"
  },
  {
    "question": "If \\(\\begin{vmatrix} 2 & 3\\ 5 & 3x \\end{vmatrix} = \\begin{vmatrix} 4 & 1\\ 3 & 2x \\end{vmatrix}\\)",
    "option_a": "-6",
    "option_b": "6",
    "option_c": "-12",
    "option_d": "12",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "\\([2 \\times 3x - 5 \\times 3] = [4 \\times 2x - 3 \\times 1] <br> 6x-15 = 8x -3 <br> 6x -8x = -3 + 15 <br> -2x = 12 <br> x=\\frac{12}{-2} <br> x = -6\\)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Evaluate \\(\\begin{vmatrix} 4 & 2 & -1\\ 2 & 3 & -1\\ -1 & 1 & 3 \\end{vmatrix}\\)",
    "option_a": "A 25",
    "option_b": "B 45",
    "option_c": "C 15",
    "option_d": "D 55",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": ""
  },
  {
    "question": "The inverse of matrix N = \\(\\begin{vmatrix} 2 & 3 \\\\\n\n1 & 4\\end{vmatrix}\\) is",
    "option_a": "\\(\\frac{1}{5}\\) \\(\\begin{vmatrix} 2 & 1 \\  3 & 4\\end{vmatrix}\\)",
    "option_b": "\\(\\frac{1}{5}\\) \\(\\begin{vmatrix} 4 & -3 \\ -1 & 2\\end{vmatrix}\\)",
    "option_c": "\\(\\frac{1}{5}\\) \\(\\begin{vmatrix} 2 & -1 \\  -3 & 4\\end{vmatrix}\\)",
    "option_d": "\\(\\frac{1}{5}\\) \\(\\begin{vmatrix} 4 & 3 \\  1 & 2\\end{vmatrix}\\)",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "N = [2 3] <br> N-1 = \\(\\frac{adj N}{|N|}\\) <br> adj N = \\(\\begin{vmatrix} 4 & -3 \\ -1 & 2 \\end{vmatrix}\\) <br> |N| = (2 x4) - (1 x 3) <br> = 8 - 3  <br> =5  <br> N-1 = \\(\\frac {1}{5}\\) \\(\\begin{vmatrix} 4 & -3 \\ -1 & 2 \\end{vmatrix}\\)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the size of each interior angle of a 12-sided regular polygon?",
    "option_a": "120<sup>o</sup>",
    "option_b": "150<sup>o</sup>",
    "option_c": "30<sup>o</sup>",
    "option_d": "180<sup>o</sup>",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "Interior angle = (n - 2)180 <br> but, n = 12 <br> = (12 -2)180  <br> = 10 x 180  <br> = 1800 <br> let each interior angle = x  <br> x = \\(\\frac{(n - 2)180}{n}\\) <br> x = \\(\\frac{1800}{12}\\) <br> = 150o"
  },
  {
    "question": "A circle of perimeter 28cm is opened to form a square. What is the maximum possible area of the square?",
    "option_a": "56cm<sup>2</sup>",
    "option_b": "49cm<sup>2</sup>",
    "option_c": "98cm<sup>2</sup>",
    "option_d": "28cm<sup>2</sup>",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "Perimeter of circle = Perimeter of square  <br> 28cm = 4L <br> L = \\(\\frac{28}{4}\\) = 7cm <br> Area of square = L2 <br> = 72  <br> = 49cm2"
  },
  {
    "question": "A chord of circle of radius 7cm is 5cm from the centre of the maximum possible area of the square?",
    "option_a": "4√6 cm",
    "option_b": "3√6 cm",
    "option_c": "6√6 cm",
    "option_d": "2√6 cm",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "From Pythagoras theorem <br> |OA|2 = |AN|2 + |ON|2 <br> 72 = |AN|2 + (5)2 <br> 49 = |AN|2 + 25 <br> |AN|2 = 49 - 25 = 24 <br> |AN| = \\(\\sqrt {24}\\)  <br> = \\(\\sqrt {4 \\times 6}\\) <br> = 2√6 cm  <br> |AN| = |NB| (A line drawn from the centre of a circle to a chord, divides the chord into two equal parts)  <br> |AN| + |NB| = |AB| <br> 2√6 + 2√6 = |AB| <br> |AB| = 4√6 cm"
  },
  {
    "question": "A solid metal cube of side 3 cm is placed in a rectangular tank of dimension 3, 4 and 5 cm. What volume of water can the tank now hold",
    "option_a": "48 cm<sup>3</sup>",
    "option_b": "33 cm<sup>3</sup>",
    "option_c": "60 cm<sup>3</sup>",
    "option_d": "27 cm<sup>3</sup>",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "Volume of cube = L3 <br> 33 = 27cm<sup>3</sup> <br> volume of rectangular tank = L x B X h  <br> = 3 x 4 x 5  <br> = 60cm<sup>3</sup> <br> volume of H2O the tank can now hold  <br> = volume of rectangular tank - volume of cube  <br> = 60 - 27  <br> = 33cm<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "question": "The perpendicular bisector of a line XY is the locus of a point B. whose distance from Y is always twice its distance from X. C",
    "option_a": "whose distance from X is always twice its distance from Y",
    "option_b": "whose distance from Y is always twice its distance from X.",
    "option_c": "which moves on the line XY",
    "option_d": "which is equidistant from the points X and y",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": ""
  },
  {
    "question": "The midpoint of P(x, y) and q(8, 6). Find x and y. midpoint = (5, 8)",
    "option_a": "(2, 10)",
    "option_b": "(2, 8)",
    "option_c": "(2, 12)",
    "option_d": "(2, 6)",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "P(x, y) q(8, 6) <br> midpoint = (5, 8) <br> x + 8 = 5 <br> \\(\\frac{y + 6}{2}\\) = 8  <br> x + 8 = 10  <br> x = 10 - 8 = 2  <br> y + 6 = 16 <br> y + 16 - 6 = 10 <br> therefore, P(2, 10)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Find the equation of a line perpendicular to line 2y = 5x + 4 which passes through (4, 2).",
    "option_a": "5y - 2x -18 = 0",
    "option_b": "5y + 2x - 18 = 0",
    "option_c": "5y - 2x + 18 = 0",
    "option_d": "5y + 2x - 2 = 0",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "2y = 5x + 4 (4, 2) <br> y = \\(\\frac{5x}{2}\\) + 4 comparing with <br> y = mx + e  <br> m = \\(\\frac{5}{2}\\) <br> Since they are perpendicular  <br> m1m2 = -1 <br> m2 = \\(\\frac{-1}{m_1}\\) = -1 <br> \\(\\frac{5}{2}\\) = -1 x \\(\\frac{2}{5}\\) <br> The equator of the line is thus  <br> y = mn + c (4, 2) <br> 2 = -\\(\\frac{2}{5}\\)(4) + c  <br> \\(\\frac{2}{1}\\) + \\(\\frac{8}{5}\\) = c <br> c = \\(\\frac{18}{5}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{10 + 5}{5}\\) = c  <br> y = -\\(\\frac{2}{5}\\)x + \\(\\frac{18}{5}\\) <br> 5y = -2x + 18  <br> or 5y + 2x - 18 = 0"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a right angled triangle, if tan \\(\\theta\\) = \\(\\frac{3}{4}\\). What is cos\\(\\theta\\) - sin\\(\\theta\\)?",
    "option_a": "\\(\\frac{2}{3}\\)",
    "option_b": "\\(\\frac{3}{5}\\)",
    "option_c": "\\(\\frac{1}{5}\\)",
    "option_d": "\\(\\frac{4}{5}\\)",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "tan\\(\\theta\\) = \\(\\frac{3}{4}\\) <br> from Pythagoras tippet, the hypotenus is T <br> i.e. 3, 4, 5.  <br> then sin \\(\\theta\\) = \\(\\frac{3}{5}\\) and cos\\(\\theta\\) = \\(\\frac{4}{3}\\) <br> cos\\(\\theta\\) - sin\\(\\theta\\)  <br> \\(\\frac{4}{5}\\) - \\(\\frac{3}{5}\\) = \\(\\frac{1}{5}\\)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A man walks 100 m due West from a point X to Y, he then walks 100 m due North to a point Z. Find the bearing of X from Z.",
    "option_a": "195<sup>o</sup>",
    "option_b": "135<sup>o</sup>",
    "option_c": "225<sup>o</sup>",
    "option_d": "045<sup>o</sup>",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "tan\\(\\theta\\) = \\(\\frac{100}{100}\\) = 1  <br> \\(\\theta\\) = tan-1(1) = 45o <br> The bearing of x from z is N45oE or 135o"
  },
  {
    "question": "The derivatives of (2x + 1)(3x + 1) is",
    "option_a": "12x  + 1",
    "option_b": "6x + 5",
    "option_c": "6x + 1",
    "option_d": " 12x + 5",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "(2x + 1)(3x + 1) IS  <br> 2x + 1 \\(\\frac{d(3x + 1)}{d}\\) + (3x + 1) \\(\\frac{d(2x + 1)}{d}\\)  <br> 2x + 1 (3) + (3x + 1) (2) <br> 6x + 3 + 6x + 2 = 12x + 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "\\(\\begin{array}{c|c} Class Intervals  & 0 - 2 & 3 - 5 & 6 - 8 & 9 - 11 & \\ \\hline Frequency & 3 & 2 & 5 & 3 &\\end{array}\\)\n\nFind the mode of the above distribution.",
    "option_a": "9",
    "option_b": "8",
    "option_c": "10",
    "option_d": "7",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "Mode = L1 + (\\(\\frac{D_1}{D_1 + D_2}\\))C <br> D1 = frequency of modal class - frequency of the class before it  <br> D1 = 5 - 2 = 3 <br> D2 = frequency of modal class - frequency of the class that offers it  <br> D2 = 5 - 3 = 2 <br> L1 = lower class boundary of the modal class <br> L1 = 5 - 5  <br> C is the class width = 8 - 5.5 = 3  <br> Mode = L1 + (\\(\\frac{D_1}{D_1 + D_2}\\))C <br> = 5.5 + \\(\\frac{3}{2 + 3}\\)C <br> = 5.5 + \\(\\frac{3}{5}\\) x 3  <br> = 5.5 + \\(\\frac{9}{5}\\) <br> = 5.5 + 1.8  <br> = 7.3 \\(\\approx\\) = 7"
  },
  {
    "question": "Find the value of x at the minimum point of the curve y = x<sup>3</sup> + x<sup>2</sup> - x + 1",
    "option_a": "\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)",
    "option_b": "-\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)",
    "option_c": "1",
    "option_d": "-1",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "y = x<sup>3</sup> + x<sup>2</sup> - x + 1  <br> \\(\\frac{dy}{dx}\\) = \\(\\frac{d(x^3)}{dx}\\) + \\(\\frac{d(x^2)}{dx}\\) - \\(\\frac{d(x)}{dx}\\) + \\(\\frac{d(1)}{dx}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{dy}{dx}\\) = 3x2 + 2x - 1 = 0  <br> \\(\\frac{dy}{dx}\\) = 3x2 + 2x - 1  <br> At the maximum point \\(\\frac{dy}{dx}\\) = 0 <br> 3x2 + 2x - 1 = 0  <br> (3x2 + 3x) - (x - 1) = 0  <br> 3x(x + 1) -1(x + 1) = 0 <br> (3x - 1)(x + 1) = 0  <br> therefore x = \\(\\frac{1}{3}\\) or -1  <br> For the maximum point  <br> \\(\\frac{d^2y}{dx^2}\\) < 0  <br> \\(\\frac{d^2y}{dx^2}\\) 6x + 2  <br> when x = \\(\\frac{1}{3}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{dx^2}{dx^2}\\) = 6(\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)) + 2  <br> = 2 + 2 = 4 <br> \\(\\frac{d^2y}{dx^2}\\) > o which is the minimum point  <br> when x = -1  <br> \\(\\frac{d^2y}{dx^2}\\) = 6(-1) + 2  <br> = -6 + 2 = -4 <br> -4 < 0  <br> therefore, \\(\\frac{d^2y}{dx^2}\\) < 0  <br> the maximum point is -1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Evaluate \\(\\int^{1}_{2}\\)(3 - 2x)dx",
    "option_a": "33m",
    "option_b": "5",
    "option_c": "2",
    "option_d": "6",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "\\(\\int^{1}_{0}\\)(3 - 2x)dx <br> [3x - x2]o <br> [3(1) - (1)2] - [3(0) - (0)2] <br> (3 - 1) - (0 - 0) = 2 - 0  <br> = 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Find \\(\\int^{1}_{0}\\) cos4 x dx",
    "option_a": "\\(\\frac{3}{4}\\) sin 4x + k",
    "option_b": "-\\(\\frac{1}{4}\\) sin 4x + k",
    "option_c": "-\\(\\frac{3}{4}\\) sin 4x + k",
    "option_d": "\\(\\frac{1}{4}\\) sin 4x + k",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "\\(\\int^{1}_{0}\\) cos4 x dx <br> let u = 4x  <br> \\(\\frac{dy}{dx}\\) = 4  <br> dx = \\(\\frac{dy}{4}\\) <br> \\(\\int^{1}_{0}\\)cos u. \\(\\frac{dy}{4}\\) = \\(\\frac{1}{4}\\)\\(\\int\\)cos u du <br> = \\(\\frac{1}{4}\\) sin u + k <br> = \\(\\frac{1}{4}\\) sin4x + k"
  },
  {
    "question": "The sum of four consecutive integers is 34. Find the least of these numbers",
    "option_a": "7",
    "option_b": "6",
    "option_c": "8",
    "option_d": "5",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "Let the numbers be a, a + 1, a + 2, a + 3 <br> a + a + 1 + a + 2 + a + 3 = 34 <br> 4a = 34 - 6 <br> 4a = 28 <br> a = \\(\\frac{28}{4}\\)  <br> = 7 <br> The least of these numbers is a = 7"
  },
  {
    "question": "\\(\\begin{array}{c|c} No & 0 & 1 & 2 & 3 & 4 & 5 \\ \\hline Frequency & 1 & 4 & 3 & 8 & 2 & 5 \\end{array}\\). From the table above, find the median and range of the data respectively.",
    "option_a": "(8,5)",
    "option_b": "(3, 5)",
    "option_c": "(5 , 8)",
    "option_d": "(5 , 3)",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "Median = \\(\\frac{\\sum fx}{\\sum f}\\) <br> \\(\\begin{array}{c|c} \n\nNo & 0 & 1 & 2 & 3 & 4 & 5 \\ F & 1 & 4 & 3 & 8 & 2 & 5 \\ fx & 0 & 4 & 6 & 24 & 8 & 25 \\end{array}\\) <br> \\(\\sum fx\\) = 0 + 4 + 6 + 24 + 8 + 25 = 67  <br> \\(\\sum f\\) = 23  <br> Median = \\(\\frac{\\sum fx}{\\sum f}\\) = \\(\\frac{67}{23}\\) = 2.913 <br> = \\(\\approx\\) 3 <br> Range = 5 - 0 = 5  <br> (3, 5)"
  },
  {
    "question": "\\(\\begin{array}{c|c} \n\nClass Interval & 3 - 5 & 6 - 8 & 9 - 11 \\ \\hline Frequency & 2 & 2 & 2 \\end{array}\\). Find the standard deviation of the above distribution.",
    "option_a": "A √5",
    "option_b": "B √6",
    "option_c": "C √7",
    "option_d": "D √2",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "\\(\\begin{array}{c|c}Class Interval & 3 - 3 & 6 - 8 & 9 - 11 \\ x & 4 & 7 & 10 \\ f & 2 & 2 & 2 \\ f - x & 8 & 14 & 20 \\ |x - \\bar{x}|^2 & 9 & 0 & 9 \\ |x - \\bar{x}|^2 & 18 0 & 18 \\end{array}\\) <br> \\(\\bar{x}\\) = \\(\\frac {\\sum fx}{\\sum f}\\)  <br> = \\(\\frac {8 + 14 + 20}{2 + 2 + 2}\\)  <br> = \\(\\frac{42}{6}\\) <br> \\(\\bar{x}\\) = 7 <br> S.D = \\(\\sqrt\\frac{\\sum f(x - \\bar{x})^2}{\\sum f}\\) <br> = \\(\\sqrt\\frac{18 + 0 + 18}{6}\\)  <br> = \\(\\sqrt\\frac{36}{6}\\) <br> = \\(\\sqrt {6}\\)"
  },
  {
    "question": "I how many was can the letters of the word ELETION be arranged?",
    "option_a": "6!",
    "option_b": "7!",
    "option_c": "5!",
    "option_d": "8!",
    "answer": "B",
    "solution": "The number of letter in the word is 7, but letter E appeared twice, therefore 7!"
  },
  {
    "question": "In how many ways can five people sit round a circular table?",
    "option_a": "24",
    "option_b": "60",
    "option_c": "12",
    "option_d": "120",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "The first person will sit down and the remaining will join. <br> i.e. (n - 1)! <br> = (5 - 1)! = 4! <br> = 24 ways"
  },
  {
    "question": "Find the probability that a number picked at random from the set(43, 44, 45, ..., 60) is a prime number.",
    "option_a": "\\(\\frac{2}{3}\\)",
    "option_b": "\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)",
    "option_c": "\\(\\frac{2}{9}\\)",
    "option_d": "\\(\\frac{7}{9}\\)",
    "answer": "C",
    "solution": "Prime numbers = (43,47,53,59) <br> N = (43, 44, 45,..., 60) <br> The universal set contains 18 numbers. <br> The prime numbers between 43 and 60 are 4  <br> Probability of picking a prime number = \\(\\frac{4}{18}\\) <br> = \\(\\frac{2}{9}\\)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Find the derivative of \\(\\frac {\\sin\\theta}{\\cos\\theta}\\)",
    "option_a": "sec2 \\(\\theta\\)",
    "option_b": "tan \\(\\theta\\) cosec \\(\\theta\\)",
    "option_c": "cosec \\(\\theta\\)sec \\(\\theta\\)",
    "option_d": "cosec2\\(\\theta\\)",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": "\\(\\frac {\\sin\\theta}{\\cos\\theta}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{\\cos \\theta {\\frac{d(\\sin \\theta)}{d \\theta}} - \\sin \\theta {\\frac{d(\\cos \\theta)}{d \\theta}}}{\\cos^2 \\theta}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{\\cos \\theta. \\cos \\theta - \\sin \\theta (-\\sin \\theta)}{cos^2\\theta}\\) <br> \\(\\frac{cos^2\\theta + \\sin^2 \\theta}{cos^2\\theta}\\) <br> Recall that sin2 \\(\\theta\\) + cos2 \\(\\theta\\) = 1 <br> \\(\\frac{1}{\\cos^2\\theta}\\) = sec2 \\(\\theta\\)"
  },
  {
    "question": "From the venn diagram above, the complement of the set P\\(\\cap\\)q is given by",
    "option_a": "{a, b, d, e}",
    "option_b": "{b, d}",
    "option_c": "{a, e}",
    "option_d": "{c}",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": ""
  },
  {
    "question": "The pie chart shows the distribution of courses offered by students. What percentage of the students offer English?",
    "option_a": "30%",
    "option_b": "25%",
    "option_c": "35%",
    "option_d": "20%",
    "answer": "D",
    "solution": "\\(\\frac{70}{360} \\times 36 = \\frac{70}{10}\\) <br> = 7"
  },
  {
    "question": "The bar chart above shows the distribution of SS2 students in a school. <br> Find the total number of students",
    "option_a": "180",
    "option_b": "135",
    "option_c": " 210",
    "option_d": "105",
    "answer": "A",
    "solution": ""
  }
]